<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Earl of Anglesey's state of the government &amp; kingdom prepared and intended for His Majesty, King Charles II in the year 1682, but the storm inpending growing so high prevented it then : with a short vindication of His Lordship from several aspersions cast upon him, in a pretended letter that carries the title of his memoirs / by Sir John Thompson, Baronet.</title>
            <title>State of the government &amp; kingdom</title>
            <author>Anglesey, Arthur Annesley, Earl of, 1614-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62416</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1565</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12627123</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12627123</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64674</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62416)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64674)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 336:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Earl of Anglesey's state of the government &amp; kingdom prepared and intended for His Majesty, King Charles II in the year 1682, but the storm inpending growing so high prevented it then : with a short vindication of His Lordship from several aspersions cast upon him, in a pretended letter that carries the title of his memoirs / by Sir John Thompson, Baronet.</title>
                  <title>State of the government &amp; kingdom</title>
                  <author>Anglesey, Arthur Annesley, Earl of, 1614-1686.</author>
                  <author>Haversham, John Thompson, Baron, 1647-1710.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Crouch ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64674:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64674:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Earl of Angleſey</hi>'s STATE of the Government &amp; Kingdom: Prepared and intended for His MAJESTY, King Charles II. In the Year 1682. but the Storm Impending growing ſo high prevented it then. With a ſhort VINDICATION of His Lordſhip from ſeveral Aſperſions caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Him, in a pretended LETTER that carries the Title of <hi>His MEMOIRS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Sir <hi>JOHN THOMPSON,</hi> Baronet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Crouch</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Pope's-Head-Alley</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_king_and_queen">
            <pb facs="tcp:64674:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64674:2"/>
            <head>TO THE King and Queen</head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it pleaſe Your Majeſties,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THIS Paper was at firſt intended a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to Your Royal Unkle; in which the Noble Author has ſtudiouſly contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted his many and large Experiences into a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs ſuitable to the Leiſure and View for which he deſigned it. How Wiſe and Great a Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man he was, and how fitted for an Argument of this Nature, by his great inſight into Men and Buſineſs, [having from his Youth breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſcarce any other Air than that of Courts] how Valued and Eſteemed by King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second for his Wiſdom and Dexterity in redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Things to their True Temper and Legal Standard, eſpecially at an Emergency, when either the Folly or Deſign of Falſe or Weak Miniſters had puzled his Majeſty's Affairs, and
<pb facs="tcp:64674:3"/>made them almoſt deſperate, Thoſe who knew him can better tell, it becomes me to be ſilent, left I ſhould Injure his Memory by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too little, or Diſpleaſe others by ſaying too much; if any have ſo much Curioſity they may themſelves make the Judgment by this Taſte that is left us of his Mind, Thoughts, and Manly, Noble way of Expreſſing himſelf, [a thing wherein his Lordſhip had a peculiar Happineſs, not diſguiſed in the Taudry Dreſs, wherein he has been of late Injuriouſly Expoſed.]</p>
                  <p>I have nothing to ſay in Excuſe for my Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in this Dedication to Your Majeſties, but that it was deſigned for the Service of the Throne, and certainly a Diſcourfe of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (wherein you will ſee the wide diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences between the Faithful and Wiſe Councils of the Dead, free from Flattery, Fear or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and thoſe of the Living, which are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to them all) cannot but be acceptable to Your Majeſties, eſpecially in a Time of ſo much Action, Danger, and Diſappointment.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Majeſties Obedient Subject and Servant.</hi> John Thompſon.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:64674:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE Tombs and Dormitories of the Dead have always been held Venerable; to Invade their Silence, or Diſturb their ſleeping Duſt, much more to Mangle, and then Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them, yet ſcarce cold, is a Crime ſo deteſtably odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, nothing but a <hi>French</hi> Barbarity <note n="*" place="margin">See the Account of the Inhumanity of the <hi>French</hi> this Summer at <hi>Heidle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg.</hi>
               </note> could ever be guilty of; but for a Wiſe and Great Man to be abuſed in his Thoughts, to be Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the World as one that took pleaſure in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving and impoſing upon the underſtanding of others, to be made to think and ſpeak things ſo low and mean, ſo dull and inſipid, nay quite contrary to his own Senſe and Apprehenſion, is a cruelty and ſavageneſs ſo much greater, as that to be Mortal, and thereby ſubject to Violence and Injury, it the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lot of all, but to be a Fool a Knave is the particular Curſe but of ſome few.</p>
            <p>And yet it bas been the Misfortume of a late Noble Lord to be thus repreſented to the World in a Book that bears the Title of, <hi>The Earl of</hi> Angleſey<hi>'s Memoirs,</hi> but is indeed ſo very unlike him, 'tis ſtrange any ſhould have the Confidence to Impoſe ſuch ſuppoſititious thing on the World; certainly this Lord might have expected better Treatment, after an Age worn out with Toyl and Pain for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, than to have his Study plundered, his Papers rifled, his Thoughts debaſed by a dull and courſe allay, and bis Reputation ſet to ſale for a little private Advantage. Is there no Original left of ſuch a Man to ſhow him to the World but this little miniature, theſe few Sheets? Where is that expected Work <note n="†" place="margin">His Hiſtory of <hi>Ireland,</hi> juſt finiſhed, as it were, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Death.</note> the Expence of ſo much Oyl and Thought, in which he might have hoped to Live to future Times? How can any that have either Value for the Memory of the Dead, or Regard for the Cenſure of the Living, detain any longer ſo uſful and ſo finiſbed a Piece, which was at firſt undertaken for the Service and Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Publick.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64674:4"/>
            <p>The Publiſher perhaps might not deſign ſo maliciouſly, but this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not the Caſe; whoever reads that Pamphlet, and believes it to be my Lord <hi>Angleſey</hi>'s, muſt think him not only a knave and Fool, but ſomewhat more. His intention ſeems only to make the beſt of his abſent Friend, by borrowing his Name to get a Penny, or to Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate himſelf with a Party in hopes of Preferment when time ſhall be; and withal, to let the World know what otherwiſe they were like ever to be ignorant of, what a Man of Worth and Weight he is. Hence are thoſe ſo frequent and repeated Praiſes of himſelf. <note place="margin">Pag. 4.</note> It is he that knows how ſoftly to inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate his Notions with the gentleneſs of a Philoſopher, <note place="margin">Pag 6</note> that has all the curious ſoft ſtrokes of Rhetorick and Reaſon, and all the Structures of a great Judgment and Fancy, <note place="margin">Pag. 31.</note> all the mixtures of great and noble Colours, able not only to prop up the great Characters of King <hi>Charles</hi> his Miniſters, but to gild the Pillory for Offenders, whoſe ſhort hints, like the ſclant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Lightning, <note place="margin">Pag. 6. &amp; 22</note> or ſudden glances by their quick movement, have power to create the Paſſions of Love and Admiration. And in ſhort, in the late Conjuncture, while the <hi>Vulgus</hi> of Writers and Lachrimiſts were aſſociated in Intailing the Popular Nuſance of Fears and Jealouſies upon us, <note place="margin">Pag. 29. &amp; 37, 39.</note> it was be alone who found out the way to remove them, by Predicting from Natural Cauſes the Happy future ſtate of our Country. And that the then Fermentation would be perfective to it; inſtead of which had he told us K. <hi>James</hi>'s forſaking and deſerting the Party that put the Crown upon his Head, the diſregarding the Opinion of his People, doing Actions that raiſed their Diſtruſt, Fears and Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, the choice of Weak and Falſe Miniſters, the taking into his Cabinet ſuch as had Abjured their Religion, the Cloſeting and Tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering with Parliaments, ſo that Nation had no hopes of having any, but ſuch as the Court were very well aſſured of, the appropriating and taking upon himſelf the Faults and Miſcarriages of his Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites and Miniſters, and in the midſt of all this, the deepeſt Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Unconcernedneſs imaginable, would at length prove Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to him, the Conſequence had certainly been much more Natural, and the Event juſtified the Prediction.</p>
            <p>But how eaſily might this have been prevented had be followed the wiſe Examples of his great Predeceſſors <hi>Edw. III.</hi> and <hi>Henry IV.</hi> who Learning by the Misfortunes of <hi>Edward II. Richard II.</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:64674:4"/>to whom he immediately ſuceeded, how dangerous the Strains of Power, and loſs of the Peoples Affections were, did the more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully maintain themſelves in the good Opinion and Love of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by granting them all the reaſonable Securities they deſired, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing their Grievances, and Removing thoſe (tho' Innocent) that were the leaſt diſtaſteful to the Commons, of which we will mention a few Preſidents.</p>
            <p>In <hi>15 Edw. 3.</hi> Declaration was made, That ſuch as found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Agrieved with the King or his Officers, ſhould upon Complaint find Remedy; and in the ſame Parliament at the Requeſt of the Commons, that the Chancellor, and all other Officers there named, may be Choſen in open Parliament, and be openly Sworn to obſerve the Laws. It was Enacted, That if any ſuch Officer died, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe his Place fall void, the King will have the Aſſent of his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and ſuch Officers ſhall be ſworn the next Parliament according to their Petition; and that at every Parliament the King will Aſſume into his Hands all ſuch Offices, ſo as the ſaid Officers ſhall anſwer to the ſaid Objections.</p>
            <p>In <hi>17 Edw. 3.</hi> The Commons Complain of the Tranſporting the Treaſure, the Diſcovery of the Secrets of the Realm, and that they neither Could nor Would (they are the Words of the Record) any longer bear ſo ſtrange Oppreſſions, hereupon the Act of Proviſion was made.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>21 Edw. 3. N. 58.</hi> The Commons Complain, That whereas di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Merchants were Slain and Robbed on the Sea by the King's E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of <hi>France,</hi> they which undertook the Coundct may be made come into this preſent Parliament to make Gree to the Merchants, who by their default have loſt their Goods; To which the King an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, Let Perſons and Places be aſſigned for hearing the Plaints of all that will Complain, to the end Right and Reaſon may be fully done to the Plaintiff.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>22 Edw. 3. N. 7.</hi> The Commons Petition, That all Wooll and other Merchandize may freely paſs; To which the King anſwers, That the paſſage ſhall be free, paying to the King his due.</p>
            <p>So in the 36th of <hi>Edward</hi> the 3d. the King conſents to a Statute for the yearly holding a Parliament. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Note,</hi> According to the practice and uſage of that time, a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſignifies a new Parliament; the ſence and meaning of the Law was, That there ſhould be a new Parliament choſe in the time preſcribed, which appears by this, that from the firſt of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third to the 14th of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, which was but 87 years; there are yet remaining, beſides what are loſt by the injury of Time, and careleſneſs of Keepers, about 72 Original Writs.</note>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64674:5"/>
            <p>So the 45 of <hi>Edward</hi> 3d <hi>Numb.</hi> 31. when Commons affirm the decay of the Navy to ariſe by three Cauſes; <hi>viz. (1 ſt.)</hi> For that ſundry Mens Ships are ſtaid for the King long before they ſerve, whereby the Owners are driven at their Charges to find their Mariners to their undoing. <hi>(2dly.)</hi> For that Merchants, the Nouriſhers of the Navy, are often reſtrained their Shipping; whereby Mariners are driven to ſeek other Trades and Livings. <hi>(3dly.)</hi> For that the Maſters of the King's Ships do take up Maſters of other Ships, as good as themſelves are; whereby the moſt of theſe Ships do lye ſtill, and the Mariners are enforced to ſeek new Livings; whereof they pray Remedy: The King promiſes to provide Remedy.</p>
            <p>Thus alſo in <hi>1</hi> of <hi>Hen. 4. Thomas Arundel</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> by the King's Command, tells them in Parliament, That it is the King's Will to Govern by the Honourable, Diſcreet and Sage of the Realm, and by their Common Conſent, and not by his own Will, nor after his own Faſhion to Rule the ſame; and further enforced, That this Realm of any under the Sun might beſt Live of it ſelf.</p>
            <p>And in the 5th of <hi>Hen. 4.</hi> At the Requeſt of the Commons, the Lords Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording that Four ſpecial Perſons ſhould be removed out of the King's Houſe, <hi>viz.</hi> The King's Confeſſor, the Abbot of <hi>Dore,</hi> Mr. <hi>Richard Durham</hi> and <hi>Crosby</hi> of the Chamber; whereupon <hi>Saturday</hi> the 9th of <hi>February</hi> the ſaid Confeſſor, <hi>Durham</hi> and <hi>Crosby</hi> came in to the Parliament before the King and Lords, where the King excuſed them, ſaying, That he then knew no Cauſe wherefore they ſhould be removed, but only for that they were hated of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and therefore charged them to depart from his Houſe according to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement; and the like he would have alſo procured againſt the Abbot, if he had been preſent.</p>
            <p>I am the more particular in theſe things, in Anſwer to that Aſſertion of the Induſtrious Mr. <hi>Prynn,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Prynn</hi>'s Preface to Sir <hi>R. Cotton</hi>'s Records, <hi>Sect.</hi> 14.</note> That the King's Created and ſet up meerly by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and their own Power in them, without any True and Hereditary Title, have ſeldom anſwered the Lords and Commons Expectations in the Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Juſt Laws and Anſwers to their Petitions.</p>
            <p>It would exceed the bounds of a Preface to go through the reſt of theſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moirs. The drift of the whole, however it be diſguiſed, is to tell the World in my Lord <hi>Angleſey</hi>'s Name, that the Buſineſs of Sir <hi>Edm. Godfrey,</hi> the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of <hi>London.</hi> the Popiſh Plot, were only Fears, Jealouſies and Surmiſes. <note place="margin">Mem P. 112.</note> That Evidence did not riſe high and clear enough to charge any Papiſt withit, however the Parliament, and a great Miniſter, threw the Guilt on them. But how probable it is that my Lord <hi>Angleſey</hi> ſhould be of this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, That he ſhould believe nothing of the Popiſh Plot, that without Malice, Motive or Evidence, he ſhould give his Voice for the Condemnation of my Lord <hi>Stafford,</hi> a Perſon he himſelf thought Innocent, that he ſhould be, firſt, ſo much a Monſter, and then ſo meer a Natural, as under his own Hand to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie as much? Whether all this looks not more like the Fiction and Forgery of the Publiſher, than the Genuine Senſe of that Great Lord, let every unpreju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced Reader judge.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64674:5"/>
            <head>The Account of <hi>Arthur</hi> Earl of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleſey,</hi> Lord Privy Seal to your moſt Excellent Majeſty, of the true State of your Majeſties Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Kingdoms. <hi>April 27th 1682.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAving by the Obligations of your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Predeceſſors to my Anceſtors and me, for ſeveral Generations lain under the ſtricteſt Bonds of Duty and Allegiance, to imploy my Studies, long Obſervation and Experience, for the furtherance of the Service of the Crown and Weal Publick, I could not contrive how to do it better and more effectually, than by offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſame to your Majeſties View and Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Conſideration, by this Scheme thereof, which is without Intreigue for any Parties Animoſity, or Envy againſt and Perſons, or Deſign of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage or Advancement to my Self or any Relation or Friends of mine. And the Nature of true Gratitude being to acknowledge and render Service for Favours received, without
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64674:6"/>Ambitious practice or expectation of further Reward or Recompence, then what ſhall free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly flow from your Majeſties Spontanious Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Conſideration, how to diſpoſe of your Subjects, ſo as may moſt advance your Glory, and render you a redoubted King to your own People, and highly eſteemed and courted by all your Allies and other Princes abroad. I have ſpent many hours to do it in the beſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner I am able by the following Diſcourſe; which is not the reſult of Melancholy and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented Thoughts, but of the moſt Serious and Dutiful Conſideration of the preſent State of your Majeſties Affairs, and how I might beſt ſerve you in contributing to render your Reign Happy and Peaceable.</p>
            <p>Your Majeſties diſcerning Judgment cannot but perceive, of what high eſteem with all your People, the Wiſe and Proſperous Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> over theſe Kingdoms is to this Day, and by what able Councellors (generally the choice of her own Wiſdom and Knowledge, not private Inclinations or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects) She ſwayed the Scepter thereof during a long Reign, to the univerſal ſatisfaction of her Subjects, and her great Honour over all the World: And how in Her time She made the right uſe of Parliaments, (Her great Council)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64674:6"/>delighting in the frequency and faithfulneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and in the unanimity of her People, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of that moſt Honourable Aſſembly well manag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, will ever be the ſureſt bond to your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and all your Succeſſors. In her time <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Flouriſhed, Religion the Darling thereof Proſpered, and was firmly ſetled; none durſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt Incroachment upon the Rights and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Subjects: The Laws had their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interrupted Courſe, and the ſeveral Benches were ſupplied with moſt able Judges, who held it their Honour and Duty to ſerve that Renowned Queen, on the Profits ariſing Legally by their Places, without further charge to the Crown or reward, but advancement to higher degrees, after long and faithful Service, which the Queen was a great Obſerver and Judge of. Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Royal Grandfather King <hi>James,</hi> as he followed her Steps, continued moſt of her Council, built upon the happy Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons She had laid; had a Proſperous and Peaceable Reign, without other Interruption then what aroſe by Heats between his Majeſty and ſome of his Parliaments, which 'tis ſome blemiſh on that time, that they were not mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſo Dexterouſly as they had been in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors times, and was an Introduction to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Miſchiefs.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:64674:7"/>
            <p>Your Majeſties Royal Father was under ſome Impreſſion from the ſame cauſe, and by the long diſcontinuance of Parliaments, diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents encreaſed, Jealouſies were fomented, and Affairs by Ill Miniſters, and the unhappy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, and Juncture of the times brought to ſuch a Criſis, that when a Parliament was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Seventeenth Year of his Majeſties Reign, and ſoon diſſolved in heat and diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, the neceſſity of Affairs and Intervening Misfortunes, and unhappy Circumſtances, ſoon brought on the great Council of the Peers, and by their advice, as the only Remedy for grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Evils, and to prevent Impending Miſchiefs, another Parliament was called and Sate the ſame Year; but by an unadviſed Act therein Paſſed, Derogatory to the Kings Prerogative, relative to Parliaments, and temporarily chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the very Conſtitution thereof, a Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was laid for thoſe Diviſions and Miſeries which enſued, and ended with the Ruine of that Parliament, and the Deſtruction of that Great Prince, to the high Diſhonour of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, but were continued by many changes of Hands and Powers, till by the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Providence of God, and Love and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of your Subjects, your Majeſty was (by a Parliament aſſembled as the Neceſlity of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64674:7"/>time required, by your honeſt Subjects Uſurping that Incommunicable Prerogative of the Crown, for the reſtitution of Monarchy it ſelf) cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led home from your Baniſhment, and reſtored to the Throne of your Anceſtors, with the greateſt and moſt unanimous Joy and Acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your People, that had been in any Age or Kingdom. And your Majeſty Reigned many Years ſince, Fond of and in Love with Parliaments, and received thoſe marks and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of their Affection and Freeneſs to your Majeſty by the ſettlement of a large Revenue, and otherwiſe, which all your Predeceſſors from the very Original of Parliaments put together had not done, to the Envy no doubt of all other Kings and Princes, eſpecially of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Enemies of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The unhappy Interruption that ſeems to be of late to thoſe halcyon days, and the occaſions thereof, are ſecrets of State which none muſt preſume to be bold with, till your Majeſties Royal Heart, which cannot but be touched with a juſt and ſad ſence thereof, ſhall incline to call for ſerious and free Councils thereupon; by which it is not impoſſible to be informed how the change hath come, and by what means your Majeſties Reign may continue ſuitable to thoſe beginnings and former happineſs, till the aged
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64674:8"/>concluſion thereof, which all your good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects wiſh you.</p>
            <p>Towards this nevertheleſs as far as I may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture in generals (and out of an honeſt and dutiful mind) without being called, give me leave to unburthen my Soul to your Majeſty as followeth.</p>
            <p>I know nothing more inclines a People to reverence and admire their King, then to ſee his Affairs, ſo governed that he needs not the Supplies of his Subjects; and that he lets them find that he is ſo far from a mind to invade their Liberties, or to advance his own Condition and Greatneſs by the Dimunition of theirs; that he counts himſelf in this happy, above the moſt abſolute Monarchs; that he is King of a Rich, Free, Stout, and Mighty People; and that he takes content Bountifully to expend his whole Royal Revenue (as your Majeſty doth, though it be double to that of any your famous Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors) for the Honour, Greatneſs, and Safety of your Kingdoms, and in Bounties to your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; wherein if your Majeſty hath exceeded (to the contracting of a troubleſome and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Debt) Councils ought to be offered how you may be extricated, and Supplies come from your Subjects in Parliament, not as the fruits of Practice and Importunity, but as grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64674:8"/>returns for beneign and good Government, as they were in the time of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Towards the accompliſhing hereof, your Majeſty may pleaſe to conſider and be informed by means that may be offered, of all the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Bounties and Favours that have flown from you ſince your Reſtoration:</p>
            <p>And have a Book prepared for you as <hi>K. H.</hi> 7. a Wiſe Prince had, of all that have Merited from, or been Obliged and Rewarded by the Crown, which your Majeſty may conſult as a Guide to you, additional to your perſonal Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Men (which is greater then any your Predeceſſors had) before you reſolve on any Grant or Bounty; wherein none ought to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune the King, but leave him to his own time and conſideration; elſe the condition of Modeſt Men will be deſperate, and the boldeſt Beggars (tho perhaps the unfitteſt Perſons) will be the ſureſt Speeders. Princes through their Bountiful Inclination and uneaſineſs at Trouble, being more ſubject to be wrought upon by Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity then other Men; but when your Majeſty upon deliberation hath ſaid the Word, let it be ſacred and unchangeable, except upon juſt cauſe avowed to the Parties ſhame.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:64674:9"/>
            <p>In my time many are grown to great Eſtates under your Majeſties Royal Father and your ſelf, and many are in a courſe to arrive at the like, whilſt your Majeſty ſinks into a Debt; from ſuch you may conſidently require diligent and faithful Service and Care, to eaſe your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and do your work; ſo that your Honour and Dignity may be ſupported, and ſo that all your Subjects may ſee and Rejoyce, that you have conferred your Favours on fuch as render themſelves Worthy thereof, and eaſe the great pains and troubles that attend ſo weighty a Crown as your Majeſties is, to which their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as well as Obligations bind them; and the ſtriſe among them ſhould be only who ſhould ſerve ſo good a Maſter beſt. I am ſure I will have no difference with nor offend any of them but upon that account, and therein I ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver doubt of Protection and Countenance from your Majeſty as far as I am truſted.</p>
            <p>I know your Majeſty hath received much diſquiet by the attempts to weaken or ſhake the Legal Succeſſion of the Crown, againſt your Majeſties deelared Reſolution to the contrary; and cannot forget that I have often aſſured your Majeſty, ſuch endeavours will be beſt diverted by wiſe and gentle handling of Parliaments,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64674:9"/>and the right uſe of your houſe of Peers in ſuch conteſts, wherein I have and ſhall ever be ready in a Parliamentary way, to do your Majeſty all the Faithful ſervice I am capable of, and to find out ſuch Expedients as may ſatisfy your People, that their Religion and Liberties may be ſecured by other ways, that ſhall neither diſpleaſe nor diſcompoſe your Majeſty, nor ſo much as raiſe in you a Jealouſie, that there is the leaſt aim to invade your Prerogative, or give you diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et or diſturbance.</p>
            <p>It is within my Memory, that the great caſe of <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> the buſineſs of the <hi>Loanes, &amp;c.</hi> were bandied in Parliament, <hi>viz.</hi> 3 of your Fathers Reign, which produced the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Right to be made a Law. After that the Caſe of Ship Money, which for more aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance after Judgment in the Houſe of Peers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it by their ordinary Authority and Power of Judicature, was branded and condemned by Act of Parliament as Illegal and Arbitrary and all the Judges queſtioned for their Extrajudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Opinions; and yet in this Caſe, not only his Majeſties Learned Council, but all the Judges upon a Caſe ſtated, were unanimous for the King Right; but being drawn <hi>Ex parte</hi> (as the other Caſes were alſo) it was very eaſy through Fear or weakneſs of Judgment, or want of the due
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64674:10"/>Ventilation and digeſtion, that cauſes of ſuch import were wont to have, after many Days hearing of Council on both ſides, and Arguments at the Bar and Bench to ingage im miſtakes; which therefore afterwards came to a publick Diſquiſition in the Court of <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> and by Writ of <hi>Error</hi> in the <hi>Exchequer Chamber,</hi> upon the oppoſition of private Subjects, who would not ſit down in a Caſe of that Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, where they conceived and were adviſed the right lay on their ſides, againſt the Opinion of the Judges; who being pre-ingaged by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial Opinions, had before both in the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> and all the Judges of <hi>England,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cext Three or Four in the <hi>Exchequer Chamber,</hi> upon the Writ of <hi>Error,</hi> given Judgment againſt the Subject, yet by the Diviſion of the Judges when it came to be a <hi>Chequer Chamber</hi> Caſe, (which I heard intirely) and the Free and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed arguing thereof, and view of the Records for ſupporting of the Liberties of the Subjects, the Eyes of People were ſo opened, that the oppoſition to the payment of it grew general; and the firſt Parliament which was called after, (as is before mentioned) put an end to that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie for ever. The Progreſs and concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Caſe ought to ſway with your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, to be wary and circumſpect in all Caſes of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64674:10"/>Law for the future, that are not warranted by known Law and Practice, appearing upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture conſideration and debate. For here was more then ordinary caution uſed, before the King would impoſe a new Burthen upn his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, though his Neceſſities were by the long diſcontinuance of Parliaments, and intervening accidents very great. And he had better vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers then are ever like to be had again in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie between the King and the Subject; and yet all came to a ſad reckoning, and raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Jealouſies which are not quite Extinguiſhed to this Day. And by attempts in new Caſes, which draw conſequences that will raiſe appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of inſecurity to the Subject may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily revive. I have always thought it more dangerous to the Crown, by colour and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Legal Authority, to do a thing of general and ſtanding import and allarm to the Subject, then without conſideration to do tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcient Acts of Violence, which I am well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red your Majeſty never will.</p>
            <p>And your Majeſty having not only by your Coronation Oath (at which I was preſent) Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally and Solemnly obliged your ſelf to the Law and Cuſtoms and good Government of <hi>England,</hi> but by many Declarations ſince in Parliament and otherwiſe, to the great ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64674:11"/>of your People of all degrees, removed the apprehenſions ſome had taken up to the contrary, and are by too many ſtill retained and improved, from the late unexpected Diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of divers Parliaments, and their proving A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bortive.</p>
            <p>I cannot but in Zeal to your Majeſties Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Safety, and that it may not be in the power of any wicked inſtruments to foment Jealouſies or to raiſe Doubts any longer, humbly beſeech your Majeſty (ſince it cannot be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that your Majeſty is skilled in the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of all the Laws) that in all caſes of Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, and which are not of ordinary Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance and Practice, but ſuch, wherein the Lives, Liberties and Properties of your Subjects in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral may be concerned: your Majeſty to the end you may perform what you intend to your People, will require the debates and advice of your Council at Law, and your Privy Council, before your Maieſty be ingaged in points of Law, that upon further Conſideration and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al will not hold, but raiſe Diſputes and bring Blemiſh upon your Majeſties Proceedings; which elſe muſt light upon thoſe whoſe Duty it is Faithfully to adviſe your Majeſty, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bounds of your Oath and Legal Pleaſure ſo often declared.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:64674:11"/>
            <p>The late War between your Royal Father and his Parliament, was little expected (as any is now) to ariſe in this Kingdom; but it came on inſenſibly and by degrees, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervening of unlooked for accidents, till it raiſed a Current that carried all before it, and had a dreadful Progreſs and Concluſion; yet the riſe of it was but Fears and Jealouſies (no bigger I may ſay then a Mans Hand Viſible to us) whaſoever might be in the Womb of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. Its true no Arming or Gathering of Forces now appears, there is no Parliament in Being, not Act in Force, for any to continue till they will diſſolve themſelves: But the ſame <hi>Engliſh</hi> People which they were wont to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, live in their own Houſes, claim their good old Laws and Liberties, and are watchful over them; who knows what the preſent Licentious paper War may produce, Its come to open quarrelling already, and quarrels bring Blood-ſhed. The ſcence is only changed, from Skirmiſhes and Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels in the Fields, and Sieges of Cities and Towns, its come now to contention in every Houſe, to altercations and Fightings between Sheriffs and other Officers, Grand Juries and Petty Juries and they and the Courts of Juſtice, who by Law are the Conſervators of our Peace, are ingaged in the quarrels, and Verdicts are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64674:12"/>found and Judgments given as the litigant par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties exceed one the other in power and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, more then by the Merits of the Cauſe, which ingageth almoſt the whole People of one ſide or other in every Caſe.</p>
            <p>So that now Juſtice hath loſt its old deep ſtill Channel, and all Cauſes are carried by a Fierce Impetuous Torrent, which in time (if not diverted) may break all our Banks, and prove a general Inundation; for its come to this already, that all Reverence to Miniſterial Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Juries, Judges, is loſt; and there is now no caſe of moment almoſt wherein there is not muſtering of Parties, and inſtead of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Appeals are made to the People, who can neither meet nor judge in a Body, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore end all Controverſies by quarrelling Parties, whoſe Judgment if it were legal can neither be known nor executed but in Parliament, where the Collective Body of your People meet by repreſentation, and where theſe ill ſymptomes of a divided and diſtempered Kingdom, can on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hope for and receive a Cure, which God and your Majeſty Grant.</p>
            <p>The Oracle of Truth hath ſaid, <hi>That a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand.</hi> Things Frame as if it were the deſign on all Hands, to encreaſe and foment Divisions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64674:12"/>of pacifying them; whence elſe is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable Licence of giving Nick Names, and Marks of Diſtinction and Reproach to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to challenge and publiſh Chartels of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance, to Scuffle and Fight in the very Streets and Coffee Houſes, and the Diſſenters in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion blamed and ſuffer for all this, as of old the cry was, <hi>Chriſtianos ad Leones,</hi> when there is ſuch a general ferment of Ranchor and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice throughout the Kingdom, as is never like to be removed, but by ſuch Remedies as ſhall be offered before I Conclude.</p>
            <p>To the diſcompoſed Eſtate of your Majeſties own Kingdoms, the disjoynted and dangerous condition of Chriſtendom, by the over-grown Greatneſs and Uſurped Dominion of the <hi>French</hi> King over other Princes and States, doth not a little contribute, and when he ſhall have leiſure and power, to finiſh his ſecret Councils and Intreigues, to Corrupt and Engage in his Deſigns, your Majeſties Diſaffected or Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Subjects, or prevail with your Majeſty to believe that his Purſe or Power and ſtrict Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with your Majeſty are neceſſary, or but probable means to ſupport your Crown and Dignity, and bridle the Subjects which his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices and Inſinuations have raiſed a Jealouſy of; it will occaſion ſuch a Paroxiſme and ſuch
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64674:13"/>Couvulſions in the State, as may dangerouſly Shake and Hazard the Peace of your Kingdoms, if not render your Great and Renowned Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment a Prey to Forreigners.</p>
            <p>But the Fatal Cauſe of all our Miſchiefs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or apprehended, and which if not by Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom Antidoted, may raiſe a Fire which will Burn and Conſume to the very Foundation; is the unhappy Perverſion of the Duke of <hi>York</hi> (the next Heir to the Crown) in point of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which naturally raiſes Jealouſy of the Power, Deſigns, and Practices, of the old Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our Religion and Liberties, and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines and Emaſculates the Courage and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy even of thoſe and their Poſterity, who have been as Faithful to, and Suffered as much for the Crown, as any the moſt pleaſed or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented in our impending Miſeries, can pretend to have done.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, though the Supreme Wheel of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence muſt be owned in all that is or may come upon us, yet every one ſeems to be at Work to dig the Kingdoms Grave; and if God hath determined our Confuſion, the leaſt accidental diſorder will too naturally bring things to a general Complaint and Quarrel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religion, Laws, Liberties and Properties, unleſs before the Gangreen ſpread further, it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64674:13"/>be by competent and wiſe Council and ſteady Government made appear, that all theſe are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, paſt the Fear or Apprehenſion of all Good and Prudent Men, and thereby that han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of Contention wreſted from the Enemies Forreign and Domeſtick of our Religion and Peace.</p>
            <p>Towards the attaining that wiſhed for end, and the delivering us from our Diviſions and Fears, and rendring your Majeſty and Kingdom Safe, Glorious and Happy; I ſhall now ſet before your Majeſty, the moſt proper Means and Remedies that occur to me, upon the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To begin with Parliaments, where your Majeſty is in your greateſt Glory, and your Kingdom in its greateſt Strength, Activity and Uſefulneſs; your Majeſty by your many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations of your Love to and delight in them, and Reſolution of frequent Aſſembling them, hath ſet ſuch an edge upon the Spirits of your People (ever fond of Parliaments) that hope de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred will make their Hearts Faints, and raiſe Jealouſies which may breed Ill Blood before their Meeting. But preparatory to a better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, it were to be wiſhed, that the licentious Liberty now taken to aſperſe the Memory and weaken the very Conſtitution and Power of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64674:14"/>Parliaments were ſeaſonably Diſcountenanced and Corrected. The blaming and reprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Parliaments, or either Houſe thereof, is a peculiar and prerogative fit for your Majeſty alone (who are the Head of them, and whoſe great Councels they are) and which is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed according to the example of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties moſt Wiſe and Proſperous Predeceſſors only in Parliament time, when they may be heard and acquit themſelves, or any Slips, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours or Faults that ſhall appear may be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, amended or redreſſed, or in caſes diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, new Remedies applied to prevent future Conteſts. And as the Peopls in general out of Parliament have no Authority herein, much leſs a part of them; ſo I count it of very pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Example and Conſequence, and no ways ſerviceable to your Majeſty by whomſoever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, that any Numbers or Degrees of Men, have preſumed (under what Colour ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver) to trample upon the Honour of Diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Parliaments, and Arraign their Proceedings, which are only to be Examined and Judged by Parliament, who can alone rectify the ſame, if found Erroneous and Unwarrantable.</p>
            <p>And I heartily wiſh this Innovation may not prove one of the greateſt Obſtacles to a good Intelligence, the next Parliament, and that it may never be queſtioned with two much heart
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64674:14"/>and reſentment, which whoſoever ſhall be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to ſerve therein, may think it their concern to do effectually, for the ſafety and preſerving the chief Priviledges and Rights of Parliament, which are Freedom and Protection (ſo that none may entertain and vent diſhonourable Thoughts of them, to the violation of their good Names or Perſons) and an Examption from being que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned or impeached in any other Court or Place but in that, the only Supreme Court of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It will be your Honour and Safety, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage and imploy your Ancient and deſerving Nobility and Gentry, whoſe intereſt in their Countries will be of more uſe and avail to your Majeſty, then all the bold and confident under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings of thoſe, who ſeek themſelves chiefly in all their pretences of Love and Duty to your Majeſty, and really weaken and diminiſh the Admiration, Affection and Eſteem, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe (from your Gracious and Wiſe Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) your Majeſty may have will all your People, who are the moſt Dutiful and fond of their Prince in the World, if well and kindly uſed, as the moſt Turbulent and Fierce under the Sun, if by ill or unſteady management of Affairs, and too much ſubjecting of them to the Will and Humour of their fellow Subjects, and the oppreſſions which their too much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64674:15"/>on his Favour brings upon them (which they eaſily diſcover (being a diſcerning People) they find themſelves transferred from the Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, Bounty nad Kindneſs of their Soveraign, and abandoned to the Pride, Malice, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious Arbitrarineſs and Will of thoſe who are but Subjects as well as they, and who want that natural Affection and Tenderneſs which their Soveraign Liege Lord cannot but retain towards them, and whoſe Wiſdom (which God who advanceth them to the Throne, uſually indues them with (muſt needs perſwade him, that he is weakned and made a leſs Monarch, by loſs of the Love and Duty of his meaneſt Subject.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Two Great Inſtruments of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with which your Majeſty in Right of your Imperial Crown, is ſolely intruſted by the Law, are Reward and Puniſhment. Let the firſt be always diſpenſed freely, freely, as your Perſonal Knowledge or the beſt information that may be had ſhall Guide you, by your own immediate Hand, that others may not receive the Thanks and Dependance due to you alone.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Henry Sidney</hi> (Great Sir <hi>Philips</hi> Father) who was Lord Deputy of <hi>Ireland</hi> many times, and my Great Grandfather Sir <hi>John Parrot,</hi> who ſucceeded him in the ſame Great Charge and Truſt; and divers others, though they refuſed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64674:15"/>not to ſerve your Predeceſſors, yet grew wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the place, when in thoſe troubled and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Times, they were forced to ſpend of their own to ſupport the Dignity and Honour of the Crown: Such as ſerve your Majeſty ſo, in expectation of future regard to be had to their deſerts, ought not to be forgotten, when higher Preferments or more profitable permanent and eaſy happen, then thoſe they ſerved in with Submiſtion and patient expectation. Nothing is more diſcouraging and offenſive to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of Subject, then to ſee Men riſe over haſtily, and before their Merits are known or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of, perhaps whilſt their Demerit hath brought them into diſeſteem; wherewas, thoſe that are advanced by juſt degrees, are ſeen Shining in Merit before they are cloathed with Honour or Preferment, rejoyce the Kingdom, and are no more Maligned, then thoſe who have ſerved their Apprentiſhips, and come to be Lord Mayor.</p>
            <p>Thus in the beſt time, Men have riſen in the Kings Houſhould, and in other Eſtabliſhments from low Degree, and after long approved Service and Faithfulneſs, to high Preferment and Truſt. And this incourageth Induſtry and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Service, and is a Bond of Safety; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as bought preferment, or attained by Ill Arts,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64674:16"/>is Odious, and Dangerous to the Maſter; and when Mony is the only qualification, People mind ſolely how to come by that, let the means to compaſs it be what they will.</p>
            <p>As for the other, which is Puniſhment, let your Majeſties Love and Clemency to your Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple make it appear to proceed from you unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and of neceſſity, for the ſupport and ſtrenthning of Government, and be ſo execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that it may not ſeem or ſo much as be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, to come from any Principle of Cruelty, or Delight in the Preſſures of Fall of any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. The known Clemency of a Prince and Inclination to Mercy, doth more to oblige Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, then the ſtrongeſt Impreſſions of Dread or Fear; it being natural to the verieſt Worm to turn again, if he be unmercifully trod upon, and deſpair to Pleaſe, or cauſeleſly conceived Jealouſy, many times occaſions the loſs of moſt Uſeful and Honeſt Servants.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I know your Majeſty to be a great Patron of the Church and Church-men, and therefore for their ſakes (who are ſeldom wiſe for themſelves) I preſume to implore, that you will never Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and of them, that ſhall buſy them ſelves with matters of State and Government, out of their Sphere. In all my Reading and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, I find, that in the moſt dangerous Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64674:16"/>and Revolutions of the World, they have ever had a principal Hand; when their chief work ſhould be to pray for and promote the Peace of Church and State, in the Calling God hath ſet them. And it never yet came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my Obſervation or Knowledge, that any Kingdom was Happy or Proſperous, where they had too great and influence, ſince the Primitive Time and Zeal, nor that ever it ſucceeded well to themſelves, or gained upon thoſe under their Charge, when they ſhewed themſelves Active in Temporal Affairs, having a Calling compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to imploy the whole Man, and are to give themſelves to all diligence and piety, wherein they are promiſed a Bleſling; as their great Maſter hath warned them, that his Kingdom is not of this World; and that they ſhould not Fight, nor Strive, nor Intangle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the Affairs of this Life. Its obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, what the pretended power of one to do ſo, <hi>In ordine ad Spiritualia,</hi> hath brought the World to, and how difficultly Incroachments of that Tribe are removed; your Majeſty is not to ſcruple the diſtinct and incommunicale ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of that Authority, which the Law gives your, and all your People have bound themſelves to acknowledge your peculiar.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:64674:17"/>
            <p>Its a hard Impoſition on your Majeſty, that you ſhould (who are the Father of your Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) be called upon to Impriſon, Conſiſcate, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh or otherwiſe Afllict and Diſtreſs any of your Peaceable and Induſtrious Subjects, becauſe other taken upon them (by what right let them conſider) to denounce them Excommunicate; that were to puniſh their Bodies becauſe their Souls are puniſhed; for the Clergy cannot ſo much as pretend a Power to go further. And the Magiſtrate hath little reaſon to hearken to thoſe Clergy-men, who are ſo diffident of their pretended Authority, that though they cry up the power of the Keys as their Office, yet when they have done, yield it to be ſo uneffectual a ſhadow of Power, as can do nothing without the Civil Magiſtrates force, below whom it is to be debaſed, to be the Clergies Executioner in puniſhing, before he have tried the Cauſe. The Magiſtrate that ſeeth a Man Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated for this fault, ſhould rather delay his Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Force againſt that Man, to ſee what effect his Excommunication will have, for the Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Sword with the Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on makes the fruit of it undiſcernable, ſo that none can ſee whether it did any thing at all, or whether all was done by the fear of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Sword. And to force Miniſters to abſolve
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64674:17"/>or give the Holy Sacrament to ſuch as had rather take it then lye in Goal and be undon, is to ſet up ſuch new Terms of Chriſtian Communion, as Chriſt never inſtituted, nor will approve, Church-Communion being a priviledge due only to Voluntiers and true Penitents.</p>
            <p>It were worthy your Majeſty to recommend for the Clergies Practice and Experience, the Grace of Self Deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, they Preach to others; for generlaly none live more eaſy and pleaſurable Lives then they; inſtead of the Primitive Auſterity, Mortification and Piety, or leſs pity, or oppoſe differences and diſorders; well were it if too many of them did not Forment and Encourage them; theſe things have brought that Contempt upon many of the Clergy, that I am ſorry to ſee, who remember the times, when for their unblamable Life, painful diſcharge of their Calling, Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitality and Watchfulneſs over Mens Souls, thoſe of their Flocks thought nothing too much, and were ready to pull out their right Eyes for them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. As a prime Foundation of your Majeſtie Greatneſs and Honour, Let the Setriement and Increaſe of your Majeſties Revenue be laid to Heart, I have often ſecretly Lamented to ſee your Majeſty, who have the greateſt and ſureſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue of any Potentate in Chriſtendom, but one, many times brought to ſuch great ſtreights by the ill manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, that I know not whether your Majeſty did not enjoy your ſelf more in the time of your Exile, being deprived of all your own, then you do now; and your Servants and Followers better contented with Hopes and Expectations, then they are now with their lank Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Retrenchments, and Suſpenſions.</p>
            <p>Towards the redreſs hereof, ſuch ſhould be ſought out and incouraged, that are able and willing to improve your Revenue to the beſt advantage, without greedy purſuit of their own priate gain, ſuch Men no doubt your Majeſties Kingdom doth afford, and may be found, and by a juſt Calculation of the vaſt Eſtares ſome have raiſed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64674:18"/>by a looſe, and deſpicable way of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deing it, it will appear, how and by what means your Majeſty becomes Poor, whilſt others wallow in your Riches; and what a vaſt detriment you are at, till this great Work be vigorouſly taken in hand and regulated, by which no doubt your Revenue may be raiſed to ſome Hundred Thouſands of pounds Sterling, above what it now amounts to. Let me bear the diſgrace of being accounted an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſter, if I Evince not what I have ſaid; and then your Majeſty will be the beſt Judge how you have been ſerved ſince your Reſtoration; though I accuſe none that have ſerved you hitherto, but deſire all Errours and Failings may be remitted and forgotten, upon condition that they who have had the misfortune (to give it no worſe a Character) of coming ſhort of doing your Majeſty that Service which is now propoſe, may with Patience and without En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy or Practice, ſee you better ſerved by others for the future.</p>
            <p>The Shrunk Sinews of your Government being thus en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged and ſtrengthned, and the deſign appearing certain to your Majeſty, I do humbly propoſe,
<list>
                  <item>1. That the greatneſs of your Houſhold may be reſtored to that of your moſt renowned Predeceſſors, this will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed advance your Honour and Eſteem bot at home and abroad. I who have live to ſee the great Hall of the Kings Houſe, and his Sollers, Buttry and Pantry full of Strangers at Dinner, and between Meals, have been hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily aſhamed to ſee the times, when a Dinner or a Cup of Wine is hardly to be had for the beſt Gueſs, nor ſo much as Food for his Councel and other great Perſons that attend in progreſs, and when the Court is in the Country. When in Parliament your Majeſty had a full and ample recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence given you for purveyance, and which will more then double ſupply the want thereof, it was little expected things would come to this paſs; but though there was then no appropriating of the Hereditary Exciſe granted
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64674:18"/>in recompence, their intention that it ſhould ſo applied did ſuſſiciently appear, and hath been generally expected.</item>
                  <item>2. The plentiful proviſion for your Houſhold, having ſet your Majeſty and Family at eaſe, the ſecond thing to be cared for, is the Security of your Majeſty and Government, by a well eſtabliſhed proviſion for your new Guards, till the unanimous Love of your People, which I will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair to ſee, may make your Majeſty judge it a Superflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Charge, and the old Guards your Majeſties Anecſtors were ſafe in, with the united affection of all your Subjects (which your will deſerve as well as any that ever ſwayed the Scepter of this Kingdom) ſuſſicient.</item>
                  <item>3. To uphold your Soveraignty of the Seas, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure your Majeſties being feared and redoubted abroad, and your Subjects accounting themſelves ſafe at home, and in their Trade and Commerce to all parts of the World, whether they ſhall carry your Name and Fame, nothing will contribute more then a powerful Fleet, which the circumſtances of Affairs, and the change thereof in that point all the World over require, ſhould much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed thoſe of your Predeceſſors; though they ever claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Dominion of the Seas; and that the beſt uſe may be made thereof, and with beſt Husbandry and moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, that your Store-Houſes, Yards and Wharfs, may be timely replenithed with all War-like Proviſions and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries whatſoever, for theſpeedy ſetting cut of Fleets to Sea, and you Ships kept always in good repair for that end; without which ſuch ſurprizes may happen as we have formerly felt, and occaſions for Service never again to be recovered, may be loſt, both being equally Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and Miſchievous to your Majeſty and Kingdoms.</item>
                  <item>4. The next thing to aſſure the Obedience of your Subjects, and to advance your Majſeſties Honour of Juſtice may run uninterrupted, this being the chief end that the chief Magiſtrates or Kings are advanced above their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64674:19"/>and have a divine ſtamp ſet upon their Authority as as Bond of Awe and Obedience. In order hereunto let your Majeſties principal Care be to chooſe freely, the moſt able and honeſt Men, and of the greateſt Integrity for Judges in all the Courts; they who puniſh others had need be very unblamable themſelves; and here it ought to be well conſidered, whether of all Perſons Judges ſhould not hold by the freeſt Tenure, and enjoy their places <hi>quamdiu ſe beme geſſerint,</hi> at leaſt, and never be diſcountenanced or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed, but upon good proof of Crimes or Offences, which render them unworthy that Truſt and Dignity, and their Puniſhment for which will rejoyce your Subjects; they of all Men ought to be placed above the Tempations of Hopes or Fears, as much as is poſſible, then Judgment will run down like a Stream, and Righteouſneſs like mighty Waters.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And where Juſtice is to ſlow immediately from your Majeſty, as towards all Officers and Domeſticks that hold by no Tenure but your Royal pleaſure, care would be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of every ſtep leading thereunto; Pick-thank Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers and Sycophants, are the worſt Inſtruments that can get into Princes Courts; but if they do, they are not to be admitted to the Kings Ear nevertheleſs if Intruders happen, let your Majeſty be ſo upon your Guard, that no Man be undermined, born down, or ruined by a Whiſper: It is but Juſtice, for your Majeſty to heart. Servant you have eſteemed, or perhaps rewarded as Faithful, before you condemn or grieve him, or to make way it may be, for a worſe prejudice your ſelf, and undo him and his Family; ſuch Errours many times coſt Princes dear: and your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution being known, to hear before you Judge, you will be delivered from Tale-bearers and mean Spirits, that have not the Courage of Honeſty to avow the Accuſations they make; and when juſt Complaints are brought before your, by honeſt and owned Informations, your Majeſty may be Judge your ſelf; whereas, otherwiſe your Majeſty is but
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64674:19"/>made the Executioner of Vile-mens Malice, Villany or Ambition, and your beſt, and moſt uſeful, and faithful. Servants may be Whiſpered from your, and your Majeſty leſt in the hand of thoſe who for Ends, Human Frailty, and deſigning Ambitious Men are ſubject to, will not ſpare to runine or betray your Majeſty for advantage; the ſame ſecret way they deſtroyed their fellow Subjects unſeen.</p>
            <p>Whereas, thoſe who intend your Majeſty real Service, will openly, and like Men of Honour (who fear the Frown of no Man) charge the Guilty for Juſtice ſake.</p>
            <p>Another main branch of Juſtice is (that you may be King of all your Subjects Hearts) To find out ways to unite your People, and for that Happy end, to avoid coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing divided and dividing Addreſſes, and Invaſions upon the Liberties and Franchiſe of your People, granted by your Royal Predeceſſors or your ſelf, eſpecially when the train and deſign of them is viſible, or hath its riſe from your own Court, or tend to ſoment heats and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents, and raiſe jealouſies.</p>
            <p>The great Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> Viſcount St. <hi>Albans,</hi> who was not only a Wiſe States-man, but Lord Chancellor of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> adviſeth the King to be of no Faction or Party, but to make uſe of and be above all, if any be in his Kingdom, or they will much prejudice his Authority and Buſineſs. If any great Man or others, be ſuſpected on good Grounds Guilty of dangerous Practice or Crime, let the Authority of the Law and not the Cry of the People (whether by Art of Inclination drawn to it, bear them down) who bawle <hi>Hoſanna</hi> and <hi>Crucify</hi> with equal Zeal even againſt their Saviour; better it were that Ten Maleſactors eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped then one Innocent Perſon ſhould ſuffer by Practice, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice or Violence.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:64674:20"/>
            <p>I ſhould rejoyce to ſee your People unanimouſly kind to your Majeſty, but for any to pretend it in diminution of better Subjects then themſelves, and in ways provok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Offenſive and Reproachful, tending to the diſquiet of your Majeſty, and diſturbance of the Peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, all Good and Wife Men from their very Souls abhor, as time will ſhaw, when this Land Flood of Contention and Humour, if not Jeſuitical Practice hath ſpent it ſelf, which it will ſoon do it not dangerouſly kept up and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced; in which Caſe as a <hi>Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand,</hi> ſo if my Fears upon ſuch Intrigues, ſucceed till the breach be wide as the Sea, I have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered my own Soul by this timely warning, which I hope you will graciouſly conſider. And the working Pens of Libellers being daily at work, to undermine our Peace and ſoment Diviſions, not unlikely imployed by the worſt Enemies of this Kingdom and Government, it will be the higheſt recomendation of your Majeſties Kindneſs to and Care of your People, that this ſoul common-ſewer of diſtempered Brains and tainted Hearts, be diverted or ſhut up, leaſt it Infect and Poyſon the whole Kingdom paſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, and render the happieſt Church and State in the World a Scorn to Fools. And to prevent ſo great Miſchief, it will be Glorious in your Majeſty, to diſcountenance e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Libellers boldly, pretending to write in ſupport of the Crown (which God be thanked ſtands os untaken upon your Majeſties Head, as upon that of the greateſt of your Anceſtors) as to puniſh others upon vain pretences, taking the ſame Licenſe; ſo that the Silencing and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all Libellers, as far as the Law will warrant, may be one happy effect of your Majeſties good and powerful Government, and when the make-bates and Sowers of Diviſion ceaſe, then mutual Love may be reſtored.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:64674:20"/>
            <p n="5">5. The laſt thing I ſhall trouble your Majeſty with, is concerning the provident management of your Revenue, which will be the greateſt help to keep all the parts of your Government in order.</p>
            <p>I know well, and can make it manifeſt beyond Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, that vaſt Reducements may be of your charge in <hi>England,</hi> to general ſatisfaction, and with the diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent only greedy Officers and Suiters, whoſe places may be better ſupplied of Meritorious Perſons or their Iſſue, who being intayled to the Crown by former Favours to them or their Anceſtors for juſt Merit, muſt be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed better and ſtronger ſupports to your Majeſty, then thoſe whoſe Ambition or Covetouſneſs makes them croud the Court, yet never intail your Favours to any, will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get Diligence and raiſe expectation in your Followers and Dependents.</p>
            <p>I beſeech your Majeſty to conſider, what great things the Crown of <hi>England</hi> hath done in former Ages, with its own bare Revenue and by the Love of his Subjects, both in <hi>England, Ireland</hi> and Foreign Countries; how your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty comes now to be in pinching wants, and none of thoſe great undertakings upon your Hands is fit to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: one thing is obvious to me, which will perſwade that other inſtances of ill management and miſpenſe may be produced. Your Majeſty ſpends now Yearly in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> full Peace, more then ſerved to defray the Charges of the Crown, in the greateſt Rebellions of the <hi>Oneils Tirones, Deſmond,</hi> and others; nay, I want not good warrant to aſſure your Majeſty, that the chief Governours proſits alone in that Kingdom, amount to more now then maintained the Government of <hi>Ireland,</hi> both in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and Military Eſtate thereof, in ſome of the troubled and dangerous times of that Kingdom, and hath incident to his Office divers Favours, Civil, Eccleſiaſtical and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary, to oblige your Subjects both Great and Small with,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64674:21"/>which ſhould moſt properly be diſpenced by your Majeſties own Hand, to weaken dependance on fellow Subjects, and fix greater and ſtronger on your Majeſty.</p>
            <p>To Conclude, Though your Majeſty is in your own Perſon above the reach of Law, and Soveraign of all your People, yet the Law is your Maſter and Inſtructer how to Govern, and your Subjects aſſure themſelves, you will never attempt the enervating that Law by which you are King, and which your have not only by frequent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, but by ſolemn Oath upon your Throne, been obliged in a moſt Glorious Preſence of your People to the maintenance of; and that therefore you will look upon any that ſhall propoſe or adviſe to the contrary, as unfit Perſons to be near you; and on thoſe who ſhall perſwade you it is Lawful, as Sordid Flatterers, and the worſt and moſt dangerous Enemies your and your Kingdom have. What I ſet before your Majeſty, I have written freely and like a Sworn Faithful Councellor; perhaps not like a wiſe Man, with regard to my ſelf as things ſtand, but I have diſcharged my Duty, and ſhall count it a Reward if your Majeſty vouchſafe to read what I durſt not but write, and which I beſeech Good to give a bleſſing to.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
